<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.3">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://kennethqngo.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://kennethqngo.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2024-11-07T05:15:24+00:00</updated><id>https://kennethqngo.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">blank</title><subtitle>A simple, whitespace theme for academics. Based on [*folio](https://github.com/bogoli/-folio) design. </subtitle><entry><title type="html">a post about drugs</title><link href="https://kennethqngo.github.io/blog/2024/drugs/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="a post about drugs"/><published>2024-11-03T17:30:16+00:00</published><updated>2024-11-03T17:30:16+00:00</updated><id>https://kennethqngo.github.io/blog/2024/drugs</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://kennethqngo.github.io/blog/2024/drugs/"><![CDATA[<h1 id="how-drug-discovery-works-from-concept-to-cure">How Drug Discovery Works: From Concept to Cure</h1> <p>Drug discovery is one of the most fascinating and challenging endeavors in modern science. It iss a process that combines creativity, scientific rigor, and increasingly, computational power to find new medicines that can help treat diseases. Let’s take a look into how this complex process works.</p> <h2 id="the-fundamental-challenge">The Fundamental Challenge</h2> <p>Discovering new drugs is like trying to solve an enormous molecular puzzle. Imagine you have a promising molecule that shows some activity against your disease target. This molecule is your puzzle, and each functional group attached to its core structure is like a puzzle piece. Here’s what makes this puzzle particularly challenging:</p> <ul> <li>Unlike a traditional jigsaw puzzle with a finite number of pieces, you have an almost infinite number of chemical groups to choose from</li> <li>Each piece you change affects how all other pieces behave</li> <li>The puzzle isn’t solved just by making pieces fit - they need to create a molecule with very specific properties</li> </ul> <h2 id="the-stages-of-drug-discovery">The Stages of Drug Discovery</h2> <h3 id="1-target-identification--validation">1. Target Identification &amp; Validation</h3> <p>Before we can start solving our molecular puzzle, we need to know what we’re aiming for. This stage involves:</p> <ul> <li>Understanding which proteins or biological processes are involved in a disease</li> <li>Confirming that modifying these targets could lead to therapeutic benefits</li> <li>Ensuring the target is “druggable” - capable of being influenced by a drug molecule</li> </ul> <h3 id="2-lead-discovery">2. Lead Discovery</h3> <p>This is where we find our initial puzzle - a molecule that shows promise but needs optimization. Scientists might:</p> <ul> <li>Screen large libraries of existing compounds</li> <li>Look to nature for inspiration from natural products</li> <li>Design molecules based on the target’s structure</li> <li>Use computational tools to virtually screen millions of possibilities</li> </ul> <h3 id="3-lead-optimization-the-molecular-puzzle">3. Lead Optimization: The Molecular Puzzle</h3> <p>This is where our puzzle analogy really comes to life. We start with a promising molecule and need to optimize it by changing different pieces (functional groups). For example:</p> <ul> <li>A methyl group might be swapped for a larger ethyl group to improve binding</li> <li>A hydroxyl group could replace an amine to enhance solubility</li> <li>A fluorine atom might be added to block unwanted metabolism</li> </ul> <p>Each change is like trying a new puzzle piece, but here’s what makes it challenging:</p> <ul> <li><strong>Multiple Objectives</strong>: Each piece needs to contribute to many properties: <ul> <li>How strongly does it bind to the target?</li> <li>Will it dissolve properly in the body?</li> <li>Can it survive long enough to reach its target?</li> <li>Is it possible to synthesize efficiently?</li> </ul> </li> <li><strong>Interconnected Effects</strong>: Changing one piece affects the entire puzzle: <ul> <li>A modification that improves binding might decrease solubility</li> <li>A change that enhances stability might introduce toxic effects</li> <li>An improvement in one property often comes at the cost of another</li> </ul> </li> </ul> <h3 id="4-preclinical-testing">4. Preclinical Testing</h3> <p>Once we think we’ve solved our puzzle, we need to verify that it works as intended:</p> <ul> <li>Testing in laboratory conditions</li> <li>Studies in model organisms</li> <li>Safety assessments</li> <li>Manufacturing feasibility checks</li> </ul> <h2 id="the-role-of-computational-methods">The Role of Computational Methods</h2> <p>Modern drug discovery uses powerful computational tools to help solve these molecular puzzles:</p> <ul> <li>Virtual screening helps predict which pieces might work best</li> <li>Molecular dynamics simulations show how different pieces might behave</li> <li>Machine learning models help identify promising combinations</li> <li>Artificial intelligence suggests novel puzzle pieces we might not have considered</li> </ul> <h2 id="looking-ahead">Looking Ahead</h2> <p>Drug discovery continues to evolve as we develop better tools to solve these molecular puzzles. The future promises:</p> <ul> <li>More accurate predictions of how molecules will behave</li> <li>Faster optimization of lead compounds</li> <li>Novel approaches to finding new starting puzzles</li> <li>Better understanding of complex biological systems</li> </ul> <p>In future posts, we’ll dive deeper into how scientists use molecular docking to predict and optimize how drugs interact with their targets.</p> <hr/>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="sample-posts"/><category term="drugs"/><category term="links"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[what drug discovery is]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Google Gemini updates: Flash 1.5, Gemma 2 and Project Astra</title><link href="https://kennethqngo.github.io/blog/2024/google-gemini-updates-flash-15-gemma-2-and-project-astra/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Google Gemini updates: Flash 1.5, Gemma 2 and Project Astra"/><published>2024-05-14T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-05-14T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://kennethqngo.github.io/blog/2024/google-gemini-updates-flash-15-gemma-2-and-project-astra</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://kennethqngo.github.io/blog/2024/google-gemini-updates-flash-15-gemma-2-and-project-astra/"><![CDATA[]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[We’re sharing updates across our Gemini family of models and a glimpse of Project Astra, our vision for the future of AI assistants.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Displaying External Posts on Your al-folio Blog</title><link href="https://kennethqngo.github.io/blog/2022/displaying-external-posts-on-your-al-folio-blog/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Displaying External Posts on Your al-folio Blog"/><published>2022-04-23T23:20:09+00:00</published><updated>2022-04-23T23:20:09+00:00</updated><id>https://kennethqngo.github.io/blog/2022/displaying-external-posts-on-your-al-folio-blog</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://kennethqngo.github.io/blog/2022/displaying-external-posts-on-your-al-folio-blog/"><![CDATA[]]></content><author><name></name></author></entry></feed>